

Kaferholzstrasse 48, Zurich-8057, Switzerland

□ (+41) 762876311 | **S** ankit@ethz.ch | **6** www.ankitjain.ch | **1** 27ankitjain

# **Summary**

A doctoral candidate at ETH Zurich with over 5 years of practical experience in microfluidics and device development. My expertise is in building automated systems with electrical, optical and microfluidic components to carry out research in biology and biochemistry.

# Work Experience

#### ETH Zurich, Institute of Chemical and Bioengineering

Zurich, Switzerland Jan, 2018 - PRESENT

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Successfully integrated electrical and optical components with microfluidic devices
- Automated workflow using LabVIEW, Python and MATLAB
- Prototyped novel devices using 3D printing and microfabrication
- Supervised several students on 3D printed droplet-microfluidic devices, phenotyping and cell/gene-recovery from microfluidic droplets
- · Successfully collaborated with biochemists, biologists and engineers for directed evolution and cell phenotyping applications

Juniper Networks Bangalore, India

HARDWARE ENGINEER

Jan, 2013 - Aug, 2015

- · Successfully delivered a high-speed board with a retiming functionality
- Took ownership of high quality hardware from concept to pre-production
- · Designed and verified of control path FPGA
- · Designed and tested of high speed PCBs
- · Collaborated with PCB layout, Mechanical, Software, Testing and Manufacturing teams

National Instruments

Bangalore, India

SUMMER INTERN Jun, 2009 - Jul, 2009

- Worked on a costumer-project on real-time signal processing using LabVIEW
- Designed and verified FPGA on National Instrument system

# **Education**

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

Dr. sc. Institute of Chemical and Bioengineering

Jan, 2018 - Present (Tentative Graduation: July, 2022)

- Thesis title: «Microfluidic droplet sorting for directed evolution applications»
  - High throughput genotype and phenotype screening and fluorescence-activated sorting in microfluidic droplets
    - Conception and development of novel absorbance-based droplet sorting and deformability-based cell sorting platform

ETH Zurich Zurich, Switzerland

MSc in Micro- and Nanosystems

Sept, 2015 - Dec, 2017

- Final grade 5.55/6
- Master Thesis title: «Ondemand digital barcodes in microfluidic droplets»

IIIT Allahabad Prayagraj, India

BTECH IN ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING

Aug, 2009 - Jul, 2013

- Final grade 9.35/10
- Bachelor Thesis title: «Qualification of 48 port 10 GE Interface Test module»

# Skills\_

Microfluidics Droplet microfluidics, Droplet sorting, Continuous-flow microfluidics, Quake-Valves, On-chip electrodes, Impedance detection,

Imaging flow cytometry, Cell sorting

**Optics** Fluorescence detection, Photothermal detection, Fluorescence Imaging, Laser-optics

**Devices** CAD Designs, Photolithography, Mask Alignment, Soft Lithography, 3D Printing

**Tools** AutoCAD, Solidworks, COMSOL Multiphysics

**Programming** MATLAB, LabVIEW, Python, Verilog, C/C++, Bash scripting

**Systems** System architecture, Board design, FPGA development, Microcontrollers, Firmware

**Biology** Cell culture and preparation, Enzyme kinetics

**Languages** English, German (B1), Hindi

JULY 25, 2022 ANKIT JAIN · RÉSUMÉ

# Publications and Conferences

# Development of a Universal NADH Detection Assay for High Throughput Enzyme Evolution Using Fluorescence Activated Droplet Sorting

Gerassimos Kolaitis\*, **Ankit Jain**\* (equal contribution), Dennis Romeis, Tomas Buryska, Matthias Steiger, Lena Wuerstl, Manuel Doering, Barbara Beer, Stavros Stavrakis, Andrew DeMello and Volker Sieber

Manuscript Submitted in ACS Catalysis; 10.26434/chemrxiv-2022-jvg5j

## Estimating the Three Characteristic Lengths of Plate-like Particles in Suspension

PIETRO BINEL, **ANKIT JAIN**, ANNA JAEGGI, DANIEL BIRI, ASHWIN KUMAR RAJAGOPALAN, ANDREW J. DEMELLO AND MARCO MAZZOTTI 2021 AICHE Annual Meeting (Manuscript submitted in PNAS)

#### Programmable Control on Multiscale volume Droplets using V-valves Integrated Microfluidic Platform

TIAN XUE\*, **ANKIT JAIN\*** (EQUAL CONTRIBUTION), XIAOBAO CAO, DAVID HESS, STAVROS STAVRAKIS AND ANDREW DEMELLO Manuscript In Preparation; Targeted Journal: Lab on a Chip

## An Ultra-fast Absorbance-Activated Droplet Sorting Platform for Directed Evolution Applications

ANKIT JAIN ET AL.

Manuscript In Preparation

# **Honors & Awards**.

- Finalist, ETH Pioneer Fellowship, 2022
- ETH Scholarship, 2017
- Juniper Networks Hardware Engineering Spot Award, 2015
- IIIT-Allahabad Academic Excellence Award (2nd highest GPA), 2010
- President's Scout (by the President of India), 2007

# **Extracurricular Activity**

#### **SKY Campus at ETH** Cofounder, President

Present Zurich, Switzerland

- Launched and lead fun meditation and yoga sessions for students
- Designed and managed Sky Campus website
- Coordinated the core team and the members

## Indian Student Association Zurich VICE PRESIDENT

Present Zurich, Switzerland

- Coorganized events for students (with around 200 participants)
- · Coordinated communication with the students, official student body of ETH (VSETH) and Indian Embassy
- Designed and housekept the organization website

## Microfluidics and Microtechnology Summer School Organizer

2018 Zurich, Switzerland

- Scouted speakers for the summer school and coordinated communication with them
- Secured additional sponsorship for the school organization
- · Managed daily events during the school

## Science Slam Zurich SLAMMER

2019 Zurich, Switzerland

• Participated in numerous Science Slam competitions in venues ranging from Scientific auditoriums to clubs in Zurich

JULY 25, 2022 ANKIT JAIN · RÉSUMÉ 2

# **Selected Projects**

#### **MICROFLUIDICS**

#### High-throughput screening of enzyme libraries

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

Jan 2019 – Present

Screening of Haloalkane dehalogenase and alcohol dehydrogenase enzyme libraries for directed evolution experiments in droplet microfluidics using a fluoresence-activated droplet sorting platform.

Development of a novel Absorbance-activated droplet sorting (AADS) platform

ETH Zurich, Switzerland
Oct 2020 - Present

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH
Developing the fastest AADS platform published to date for directed evolution applications.

Development of a high-throughput cell-deformability-based sorting platform

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

Prof. Andrew deMello, ETH Zurich

Aug 2021 – Present

Electrically actuated cell-sorting platform based on cell-deformability in a non-newtonian viscoelastic fluid.

On-demand digital barcodes in droplets

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

Prof. Andrew deMello, ETH Zurich

Mar 2017 - Dec 2017

Generation of on-demand monomer droplets, photo-polymerization and subsequent loading into an encapsulating droplet for barcoding applications.

## Microfluidic platform for the large-scale screening of C. elegans

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. ANDREW DEMELLO, ETH ZURICH

Apr, 2016 – Jul, 2016

Developed an image-based automated platform for worm loading, trapping using on-chip pneumatic valves and worm release.

#### MEMS AND MICROFABRICATION

#### **Fabrication and characterization of MEMS acoustic sensors**

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

PROF. CHRISTOFER HIEROLD, ETH ZURICH

Feb, 2016 - Aug, 2016

Aided in the development of coupled mass-based MEMS acoustic sensors. The tasks included design of test structures, etching (RIE) of devices, imaging using SEM, and characterization via Laser Doppler Vibrometer.

#### Fabrication and characterization of a MEMS accelerometer

ETH Zurich, Switzerland

EMBEDDED MEMS LAB PRACTICAL COURSE, ETH ZURICH

Oct, 2015 - Nov, 2015

#### BOARD AND FPGA DESIGN

#### Design of 4X100GE CXP optics based physical interface card

Bangalore, India

JUNIPER NETWORKS, BANGALORE

Sep, 2013 – Jul, 2015

Designed and tested a high-speed PCB that housed four 100GE CXP optical interfaces, Regenerative repeaters (retimers), a control path FPGA, and associated clocking, power and miscellaneous control devices.

## Qualification of 48 port 10 GE interface test module

Bangalore, India

JUNIPER NETWORKS, BANGALORE

Apr, 2013 – Jun, 2013

Tested PCB which was used for validating various types of interfaces such as 10GE, I2C, SGMII, PCIe and MDIO. The board housed regenerative repeaters for looping back 10GE traffic, control path CPLD, and various power loads.

# Implementation of a JPEG encoder on FPGA

Prayagraj, India

Prof. Dr. Neteesh Purohit, IIITA

Jan, 2012 – May, 2012

Developed and implemented an efficient architecture for JPEG image compression encoder with a 2-stage pipeline without using any hardware multipliers (just for fun).

JULY 25. 2022 ANKIT JAIN · RÉSUMÉ 3